Great, as פסח Pesach soon approaches, our דף Daf is ע"ב, Ayin
Bais, and we pick up about five lines from the top, last
word of the line, ההוא. Hahu. We're in the middle of the
issue here about selling wine to a non-Jew which led to all
these questions about how do you finalize a sale with a non-Jew,
and we discussed תוספות Tosafot discussed selling an ear of the animal
so to get out of בכור Bechor and then we discussed the
relevance of all that for selling חמץ. Chometz. Anyway, so it's now
we so now
because we're in these issues about sale and when is a sale
final, we have a little bit of a digression before the משנה
Mishnah which really has very little to do with what we've talked
about until now. ההוא גברא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hahu gavra d’amar lei
l’chavrei, somebody said to his friend, where were we? ע"ב עמוד א,
Ayin Bais amud aleph, five lines from the top, last word on
the line. ההוא גברא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hahu gavra d’amar lei l’chavrei,
אי מזבינא לה מזביננא לה לך להא ארעא, Ei mazvina lah mazvinana
lah lach l’ha ara, if I ever wind up selling this land,
לך מזביננא, Lach mazvinana, I'll sell it to you. And apparently they
did some קנין kinyan on that. Okay, some handshake or סודר, sudar,
well not a handshake, let's say a קנין סודר. kinyan sudar.
אזל זבנה לאיניש אחרינא, Azal zavnah l’inish achrina, then in the passage
of time the guy went and he sold it to somebody else.
He broke his promise. So אמר רב יוסף קנא קמא. Amar Rav
Yosef kana kama. No, the sale to the second didn't work, the
first one owns it. Now,
the assumption here is a, that there's a קנין kinyan although that
wasn't mentioned. It was some type of a סודר sudar or else
how could the first one own it? But b, that what you
did when you did that קנין kinyan is you didn't just make
like a promise, I promise I'm going to sell it to you.
Cause that's like a discussion in the beginning of בבא בתרא, Bava
Batra, קנין דברים, kinyan devarim, like you know, even if you do
a קנין kinyan on a promise, there's no bindingness, legal bindingness to
the promise. You know what I mean? Even like in American court,
sometimes you can sue for breach of contract, of oral contract, but
that's just like getting, you know, even if the court will recognize
that, that's just for like you know getting some type
of damages. It's not actually that the sale is final if it
was just a promise to sell. So anyway, so what you have
to assume here is that he didn't just say I promise to
sell and did a קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, that actually they did
a קנין סודר kinyan sudar on the sale. So I went ahead
and I said to my good friend Gloria, Gloria, if I ever
wind up selling this land, I haven't decided if I'm going to
sell it, but if I ever wind up selling it, I'm going
to sell it to you, let's do a קנין kinyan right now
on the land that will be effective if and when or retroactively
from the day that I decide to sell it. So you have
to assume that's the context, because if that's not the context, the
question is like a moot point, obviously it's just a promise it
didn't take effect. Okay, and רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, assuming that
type of a context, that it actually worked. So אמר ליה אביי,
Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye challenged רב יוסף Rav Yosef and
he said to him, והלא לא פסק, Vehalo lo pasak, but they
didn't set a price. So even if you did a קנין kinyan
on the land a year ago, a month ago, ten years ago
when you said that if I wind up selling it I'll sell
it to you, you never agreed upon a price and therefore the
קנין kinyan cannot be final. No קנין kinyan is final if the
price isn't agreed upon,
even if you did the מעשה קנין. ma'aseh kinyan. וממאי תאמר דכל
היכא דלא פסק לא קנה? U’mimai teamar d’chol heicha d’lo pasak lo
kana? And where do I know this from, that if you didn't
set a price the קנין kinyan doesn't take effect? דתנן, Detnan, we
taught in our משנה. Mishnah.
המוכר יינו לעובד כוכבים פסק עד שלא מדד דמיו מותרין. Hamocher yeino
l’oved kochavim pasak ad shelo madad damav mutarin. וממאי תאמר, U’mimai teamar,
from אומר, omer, where do I know this from? Where do I
say this from? Okay. המוכר יינו לעובד כוכבים פסק עד שלא מדד
דמיו מותרין. Hamocher yeino l’oved kochavim pasak ad shelo madad damav mutarin.
מדד עד שלא פסק דמיו אסורין. Madad ad shelo pasak damav asurin.
If the guy did a משיכה, meshichah, took possession of it after
you fixed the price, then it's okay, he owns the wine before
he had a chance to touch it. But if he took possession
of it before you fixed a price, then it's forbidden, because he
doesn't own it yet because the price hasn't been fixed and he
touched it or he had an ability to touch it and now
it's your סתם יינם stam yeinam and therefore you can't get benefit
from it because he doesn't own it yet and now it became
forbidden. So you see in our משנה, Mishnah, the sale is not
final until after there was a fixing of the price. So that's
a pretty darn good proof okay that no sale works if you
haven't fixed the price. So הגמרא hag'mara says, מאי הוי עלה, mai
hava alah, okay that was a good response אביי Abaye had to
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, what was therefore the conclusion? So הגמרא hag'mara
says, מאי הוי עלה, mai hava alah, what was the conclusion? כדאמרין,
Kedamrin, like you just said, אביי Abaye had a slam dunk proof
against רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. No sale is final without a fixed
price. What's the question? רב יוסף Rav Yosef was wrong. So הגמרא
hag'mara says no, דילמא חומרא דיין נסך שאני. dilma chumra d’yayin nesech
shani. Maybe under normal laws of מקח וממכר mekach u’memkar of transactions
we would say if you do a קנין kinyan even without a
fixed price it's final. But in our משנה Mishnah because we're strict
by יין נסך, yayin nesech, we're going to say maybe it's not
totally final and therefore he had a chance to touch it before
he owned it and therefore it's a problem. So maybe in our
משנה Mishnah we're being strict to say it wasn't totally final because
of יין נסך yayin nesech issues, but maybe in general. In general
monetary matters we would say it is final. So you can't a
hundred percent prove it from the משנה. mishna. So let's see if
there's somewhere else we can prove אביי's Abaye's point from. Fine. So
the גמרא Gemara says תא
שמע, Ta Shma, come in here. דאמר רב אידי בר אבין, D'amar
Rav Idi bar Avin, עובדא הוה בי רב חסדא, Uvda hava bei
Rav Chisda, there was a story like this in the house of
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, רב חסדא ברי דרב הונא, Rav Chisda brei
d'Rav Huna, and רב חסדא Rav Chisda had a story like this
in the house of רב הונא, Rav Huna,
ופשטה u'pashtah and בי bei here might mean also the בית מדרש,
Beis Medrash,
ופשטה מהא דתנן, u'pashtah meha d'tenan, and they concluded it from the
following משנה, mishna, a משנה mishna that's not about יין נסך, yayin
nesech, but's all about finalizing a sale. משך חמר ופועליו. Mashach chammar
u'poalav. Here I am, I'm buying some oranges from a good friend
Gloria, and Gloria's having them delivered to me. And she sends them
through a donkey driver who's got all these sacks of oranges on
the donkey. Or on a, she sends them with her delivery guy,
and he's got these sacks of oranges on his back. Now I
go ahead and I draw the, you know, I lead the delivery
guy or the donkey driver into, ויכניסם לתוך ביתו, v'hichnisam l'toch beito,
and bring them into my house. Okay.
So בין פסק עד שלא מדד ובין מדד עד שלא פסק, bein
pasak ad shelo madad u'vein madad ad shelo pasak, so in that
case where they're still on the backs of the delivery guy or
of the donkey, I can't take possession of them. They're, you know,
somebody else is holding on to them. So whether I did, we
agreed to the price before I drew, brought them into my house,
or I brought them into my house and then we agreed on
the price, it really doesn't matter, the sale isn't final. They're on
the backs of the delivery boy. שניהם יכולים לחזור בו, shneihem yecholim
lachzor bo, both of them, לא קנה, lo kana, it doesn't work,
ושניהם יכולים לחזור בו, u'shneihem yecholim lachzor bo, either of us can
retract the sale, it's not final. פרקן, Parkan, if I unloaded them
from the delivery truck or whatever, the donkey, והכניסם לתוך ביתו, v'hichnisam
l'toch beito, and then brought them into my house,
then is it final or not? It depends whether we fixed a
price. פסק עד שלא מדד, Pasak ad shelo madad, אין שניהם יכולים
לחזור בהן. ein shneihem yecholim lachzor bahen.
If we fixed a price before I drew them into my house,
the sale was final. I did משיכה, meshikha, not only משיכה, meshikha,
I did קנין חצר, kinyan chatzer, they're in my house. Okay. But
the key is I did a קנין kinyan and there was a
fixed price. Now the sale is final. מדד עד שלא פסק, Madad
ad shelo pasak,
however, if I weighed them, brought them into my house, and we
have yet to fix a price, even though I physically took possession
of these crates of oranges and they're in my house, since we
haven't fixed a price, שניהם יכולים לחזור בו, shneihem yecholim lachzor bo,
either of us can retract. So that is a quite explicit משנה
mishna that even with the biggest קנינים kinyanim in the world, if
you don't have a fixed price, the קנין kinyan isn't, the sale
isn't final. Okay. And therefore in this case, even though I agreed
to sell Gloria my field and maybe we even did a קנין
kinyan so she'd take possession of the field, since there was no
fixed price, the sale was not final. Very nice. Now the גמרא's
Gemara gonna have another story like this. ההוא גברא דאמר ליה לחבריה,
Hahu gavra d'amar lei l'chaverei, somebody said to his friend, I went
and I said to Gloria, same thing, אי מזבנינא לה
להא ארעא, ee mizbanina lah l'ha ara, if I'm ever gonna sell
this plot of land, מזבנינא לך במאה זוזי, mizbanina lach b'mea zuzei,
I will sell to you with a hundred, for a hundred זוז.
zuz. So we set a price, a hundred dollars, and we did
a קנין, kinyan, and the קנין kinyan was just conditional on the
fact that I, if I ever decide to sell it, then this,
then you should take possession of it as of now through this
קנין kinyan with a hundred dollars. Okay. So it should work if
I ever decide to sell it. אזל זבנה לאינש אחרינא, Azal zabnah
l'inash acharina, but then I went ahead and I sold it to
some other person, במאה ועשרים, b'mea v'esrim, because this other guy was
offering me a hundred and twenty. So אמר רב כהנא קנא קמא,
amar Rav Kahana kana kama, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana said Gloria
owns it. You decided to sell it, so your original transaction with
Gloria is effective. מתקיף לה רב יעקב מנהר פקוד, Matkif lah Rav
Yaakov mi'Nehar Pekod, רב יעקב מנהר פקוד Rav Yaakov mi'Nehar Pekod challenged
this. He said, היי זוזי אנסוה, hai zuzei ansuh, you,
I was forced by the temptation of money, by the high offer
that the guy was willing to pay more than the actual market
rate for that field, and therefore my sale to Gloria is not
final. Now why not? Didn't I sell it to her on a
stipulation, on a condition, and the condition was met?
So you know, it sounds like you could frame this in one
of two ways. You could frame this as number one,
like yes, technically the condition was met, but in my mind, I
only meant if I'm ever gonna sell it at the market rate,
I'm gonna sell it to you. Like I never, it never occurred
to me that somebody would offer me so much more money. And
had somebody, and that was never part of my implicit stipulation to
Gloria. I never meant to include a case where I was offered
such an excessive amount of money. In that case I never would've
wanted to sell it to her. I would've wanted to go where
the money was. Okay. So that's one thing, like it's implicitly a
limitation of my agreement or of my stipulation with Gloria. was a
case like that. Okay, of course, you know, like I mean, don't
try to use that in a secular court of law. I mean,
the whole reason people enter into these contracts, right, with like they
have the, you know, that they
buy what-not-what's-it-called, not the right of first refusal, but the-but-anyway, they, you
know, Gloria, you should know, you must know this, when like you're
dealing with like real estate, an option, right, to buy and so
on, you can't say, well, I never would have sold you the
option had I realized I was going to be given- the whole
point of the option is that you can exercise it. Okay, but
anyway, but that's like- those are usually oral contracts. Well, yeah, but
I don't know, that's an interesting question, like- oral contracts in American
law don't cover real estate. Right, that's a- that's a good question,
like would it have been different if it was written and then
we would have thought that you didn't have as many qualifications, right?
So anyway, so anyway, but that- so the other way of sort
of saying it, a more extreme way, by the use of the
word אונס, ones, the money forced me, is it's almost like I'm
saying like I wasn't looking to sell it, I only agreed to
sell to Gloria if I chose to sell it. Here I didn't
choose to sell it, I was forced to sell it, because somebody
made me an offer I couldn't refuse. Okay, and when I said
I'll give it to you if I want to sell it, it
means if I'm deciding to sell it, not if I'm being pressured.
So the money is pressuring me. Anyway, it's- either way it's pretty
interesting that that allows me to get out of my deal. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
והלכתא כרב יעקב מנהר פקוד, Vehilchata k'Rav Yaakov me-Nehar Pakod, and we
rule like the latter position, which is pretty amazing.
Now let's say not a case where I'm being tempted by some
other offer, I give- I sell it to Gloria on- based on
the price, and remember we have to fix a price, but I
don't give an actual number for the price. Here's what I say
for the price. אמר ליה, Amar lei, I say, כדי שיימי בתלתא.
K'deshaimi bitlata. I'll sell it to you based on the value as
assessed by three people. So since I mentioned three people, I mean
three- the normal assumption is I mean three men, and I mean
a בית דין. Beit Din. And the word שיימי, shaimi, שומא, shuma,
which is like an- to assess- שומא Shuma is to assess- assess,
means like an act that בית דין Beit Din does, you know,
they send an assessor and they- and they evaluate it or whatever.
So it means based on the decision of a בית דין. Beit
Din. So שמא shamai was an assessor, שמא. shama. Really? That really
true? Okay, כדי שיימי בתלתא. K'deshaimi bitlata. What if I say that?
אפילו תרי מיגו תלתא. Afilu try migu tlata. It doesn't have to
be a consensus of three. Since I am implicitly creating them as
a בית דין, Beit Din, okay, then that means any two votes
wins. So even if two out of three people agree upon a
price, that determines the price that now I'm going to sell it
to Gloria for even if the third one dissents. Now the other
question is of course which בית דין Beit Din are we talking
about, right? If you want to say a בית דין, Beit Din,
who gets to pick which בית דין Beit Din and which three
people? We'll get to that later. If I say כדי אמרי בתלתא,
K'de'amri bitlata, not 'as is assessed by three', but 'as three people
will say'. So that- the word 'will say', that verb is not
like a בית דין Beit Din type of an act. Okay, and
therefore I'm not conceptualizing them as a בית דין, Beit Din, and
in that case עד דאמרי בתלתא, ad de'amri bitlata, they all have
to agree and they all have to- have a consensus of the
same price point.
כדי שיימי בארבעה, K'deshaimi b'arba'ah, now let's say I say 'as is
assessed', so that's a verb used by בית דין, Beit Din, but
I say with four. Four is not a בית דין. Beit Din.
Okay, so I'm presumably now no longer operating in the בית דין
Beit Din model. Wait a minute, the בית דין Beit Din is
a max of three? Well, it usually is three and anyway- and-
and even if it's more, it's- it's an odd number. Four is
not- if I had said the word כדי שיימי בבית דין בארבעה
k'deshaimi be-Beit Din b'arba'ah it would have been different, but my presumption
when I'm saying four is that I'm not referring to a structure
of a בית דין. Beit Din. So if I say כדי שיימי
בארבעה, K'deshaimi b'arba'ah, עד דאמרי בארבעה. ad de'amri b'arba'ah. Similarly, it goes
by the four have to- have to have a consensus of what
the value is.
וכל שכן היכא דאמר ליה כדי אמרי בארבעה. V'chol sheken heicha de-amar
lei k'de'amri b'arba'ah. Certainly if I say 'if four say', that I
don't even use a verb that's used by בית דין. Beit Din.
Okay, אמר ליה כדי שיימי בתלתא. Amar lei k'deshaimi bitlata. Now let's
say I say 'as three assess it' and we say that means
that I'm structuring them as a בית דין Beit Din and it's
any- whatever the- agreement of is of two out of the three.
דאתו תלתא ושמוה, De'atu tlata v'shamua, and the three went and they
assessed it. ואמר ליה אידך, V'amar lei idach, and now the other
one says, I don't know who's the one and who's the other
one, but let's say anyway a בית דין Beit Din I pick
assesses it. And then Gloria comes and says, ליתו תלתא אחריני דקימלהו
טפי. Leitu tlata achrinei d'kimlehu tfei. These guys don't know their job,
these guys are not expert assessors. I want a different- we agreed
that you sell to me at the price as defined by a
בית דין. Beit Din. I want a more expert בית דין Beit
Din to come and assess it, which seems like a reasonable point
since nobody identified which בית דין Beit Din are we talking about.
It does sound like implicitly if I'm the one selling it, I
implicitly have the right to choose the בית דין, Beit Din, right?
It's not like it's totally up in the air. But if Gloria
has a claim, a very specific claim, not just I want to
pick my own בית דין. Beit Din. Tough luck you want to
pick your own בית דין, Beit Din, I'm the one selling it.
But if her claim is these guys aren't expert, then maybe we
say, ah, well that's already a legitimate claim and then maybe we
get to- she gets to pick. pick a different בית דין. Beis
Din. Okay? So that's what רב פפא Rav Pappa says. אמר רב
פפא דינא הוא דמעכב. amar Rav Pappa dina hu dema'akeiv. In that
case, Gloria has a legitimate claim why she doesn't want to use
the בית דין Beis Din I picked. She has a right to
object. And then, I don't know, she gets to pick another בית
דין, Beis Din, I get to pick it, but she—as long as
she can't object to it, okay? But she has the right to
make that objection.
מתיב ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, maskiv lei Rav Huna brei
deRav Yehoshua, Rav Huna challenged this. ממאי דהני קימלו טפי, mimai dehani
kimlu tefei, who knows—why should we presume that Gloria is right? Who's
to assume that the next בית דין Beis Din is any more
expert than the first בית דין? Beis Din? דילמא הני קימלו טפי,
dilma hani kimlu tefei, maybe this one is more expert. והלכתא כרב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע, vehilchata keRav Huna brei deRav Yehoshua, and we
rule that way, that just because she raises an objection doesn't mean
that she is correct. Now, it sounds like—it sounds like let's say
she just סתם stam says it without any backup evidence. Okay? Then
it's like, well, how do we know she's right? But let's say
she actually has backup evidence. Let's say Gloria actually says, "You know,
these guys never have no experience, I've never seen them assess property
before, they're not licensed, etc., etc." Is that a good objection? So
it sounds like the answer is that's still not a good objection,
because how do you know the next בית דין Beis Din will
be any better? But okay, but let's say you do know the
next בית דין Beis Din will be better. Let's say Gloria will
say, "I want a בית דין Beis Din that's licensed," you know,
as assessors. So then presumably it is a good claim. Anyway, real
estate agents, it's not exactly clear. Like, you know, it doesn't sound
like fundamentally she can't object; it just sounds like she can't object
out of thin air. Like, you need some concrete basis to a
claim that this בית דין Beis Din doesn't know enough what they're
doing and b that the other one will be any better. Okay,
anyway, that was a bit of a digression. Back to יין נסך.
Yayin Nesech.
Next משנה: Mishna: נטל את המשפך ומדד לתוך
צלוחיתו של עובד כוכבים. natal es hamashpeich umadad lesoch tzluchiso shel oveid
kochavim. אסורה. asura. So you have a funnel and you've got your
barrel and you're going to put your funnel in the, you know,
wine bottle of the non-Jew and pour from your bigger pitcher through
the funnel into the wine bottle of the non-Jew. וחזר ומדד לתוך
צלוחיתו של ישראל. vechazar umadad lesoch tzluchiso shel Yisrael. Now there's a
concern that there's some wine left in the funnel from when you
poured into the non-Jew. Now, it's all kosher wine. But when it
hits the vessel of the non-Jew's—you know, the bottom of the non-Jew's
wine bottle—look, it's sort of like this case I've got here, except
all we have to do is add a funnel. Okay? So here's
your
funnel. Alright? And here is, right, the wine bottle of the
whatever, of the non-Jew. So when the wine, right, goes in here
and hits here, here it's kosher; when it hits here it becomes
יין נסך. Yayin Nesech. Maybe because he's got some drops of wine
there, maybe because what hasn't yet been fully cleared is once he
takes possession of it, in theory he has the ability to touch
it and therefore it becomes יין נסך. Yayin Nesech. So the wine
when it hits here is יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, okay? Here it's
kosher. Then you're going to take this funnel and now use it
for, right, to sell to a Jew. And it has presumably some
drops of wine left in it. And the assumption is, because you
poured it here and here it mixed with or became יין נסך,
Yayin Nesech, the drops of wine that are now in the funnel
are also problematic and now you're going to use it for a
Jew and now you got a problem, because now the Jew is
going to get some of that יין נסך Yayin Nesech mixed up
in his wine. Okay? So let's take a look. וחזר ומדד לתוך
צלוחיתו של ישראל. vechazar umadad lesoch tzluchiso shel Yisrael. אם יש בו
עכבת יין אסור. im yesh bo akavas yayin assur. Okay? If there
is some type of holdback of the wine, some type of remnant
of the wine from the first pouring, then it's still a problem.
Some of the גרסה, girsa, עכבת akavas with a קוף, kuf, from
I guess the word
עקב, akeiv, the footsteps of the wine, footprints of it. Anyway, if
there's some remnant of the wine left in that funnel, it's a
problem.
המערה מכלי לכלי את שעירה ממנו מותר ואת שעירה לתוכו אסור. hama'areh
michli lichli es she'ira mimenu mutar ve'es she'ira lesocho assur. If you
are pouring from one vessel to the next, what you're pouring from
is permissible and what you're pouring into is forbidden. Okay? Which basically
means—okay, we're going to talk about whether is it a Jew pouring
or a non-Jew pouring. But basically, if we talk about a Jew
pouring into the non-Jew, it sounds like what it's saying is, here
you're pouring מכלי לכלי, michli lichli, when it hits the vessel of
the non-Jew it's forbidden, but what remains in your vessel is permissible,
which is totally fine. Okay, except—so what remains in your vessel is
permissible, but somehow the stuff in the funnel is forbidden. So we're
going to have to figure out: why is the stuff in the
funnel forbidden? The stuff in the funnel never got into the vessel
of the non-Jew. So that's going to be—and now finally, finally we
are going to get to the discussion which we have been alluding
to or referring to for many דפים, dappim, which is the question
of
whether
ניצוק הוא חיבור. nitzok hu chibur. Okay, תנן התם. tnan hatam. We
taught over there in a Mishnah in
טהרות. Taharos. הניצוק, ha'nitzok, ניצוק nitzok is exactly a case like this.
Okay, this is ניצוק. nitzok. You have wine that is sort of,
you know, pouring down from one vessel and it's whatever, it's going
somewhere else. Okay, that's ניצוק. nitzok.
Okay, that's ניצוק. nitzok. הקטפרס, ha'katafres, קטפרס katafres is that it's going
down at an angle. Okay, so here, you have stuff that's going
down here. Okay, this is קטפרס. katafres.
And
ומשקה טופח. u'mashkeh tofe'ach. משקה טופח mashkeh tofe'ach means here you've got,
you know, let's say you've got this little amount, this amount of
liquid, this amount of liquid and between them you've got a very
thin layer of liquid. And that's משקה טופח. mashkeh tofe'ach. Now, that
is contrasted to טופח על מנת להטפיח. tofe'ach al menat le'hatpi'ach.
Okay, טופח tofe'ach means there's a thin layer of liquid, okay, but
if I touch it like, you know, my hand will get wet,
okay, but what is טופח על מנת להטפיח? tofe'ach al menat le'hatpi'ach?
טופח על מנת להטפיח tofe'ach al menat le'hatpi'ach is I touch it
and I lift my hand off and there's enough moisture left on
my hand that now if I were to go ahead and touch
something else, that other thing would get wet. Okay, that's טופח על
מנת להטפיח. tofe'ach al menat le'hatpi'ach. It's enough that you can actually
transfer it somewhere else. טופח tofe'ach is a thinner layer. It'll get
your hand a little bit wet, but you won't be able to
touch something else and get it wet. So the question by all
of these things is well the next line in the Mishnah is
all of these things are
חיבור
לטומאה ולטהרה—I'm chibur le'tumah u'letaharah sorry, אינו חיבור לא לטומאה ולא לטהרה.
eino chibur lo le'tumah velo le'taharah. Is not a connection for טומאה
tumah and טהרה. taharah. But האשבורן, ha'ashboren, if it's like a collection
of water, a pool of water, חיבור לטומאה ולטהרה chibur le'tumah u'letaharah
is a חיבור. chibur. So what does it mean חיבור לטומאה ולטהרה?
chibur le'tumah u'letaharah? I'll give you an example. Let's say here I
am
and I'm טמא, tamei, and I touch, okay, this little collection of
water here. I make that collection of water טמא. tamei. Did this
water become טמא? tamei? Was it like it was one big unit
or not if they're only connected by this tiny thin film? Let's
say I touched
here. Did I make all of this water טמא tamei or fruit
juice or whatever it would be, wine or whatever it would be?
Okay, or you could say I touched up here. Did I make
the stuff down here טמא? tamei? Okay, I mean eventually if it
rolled down that's a different story, but do you look at it
all as one unit? Okay,
I went ahead and I touched this. Did that make the stuff
at the bottom טמא? tamei? Before the, obviously some of it will
get into it, it'll be a different story. Or I touched the
bottom, did I make this top טמא? tamei? Okay,
that's the question whether ניצוק nitzok and קטפרס katafres is a חיבור.
chibur. You got that? So if it says it's not a חיבור
chibur it means I did not make them טמא. tamei. That's it's
not a חיבור לטומאה. chibur le'tumah. Okay, what is לטהרה? letaharah? So
לטהרה letaharah is that if let's say I've got here a מקווה.
mikvah. Okay, I have here a kosher מקווה, mikvah, and it's got
this thing, and here I've got a little collection of water which
is connected because you know here's a smaller
well that doesn't have forty סאה, se'ah, but they're connected through this
string. If it's considered one unit, then when I go into the
מקווה mikvah here, it's one big long מקווה mikvah and it's like
one big body of water and I'm טהור tahor because this connects
them. Okay, and similarly in this case, all these types of cases,
right? I've got
two wells. Okay, this one has forty סאה, se'ah, this one has
twenty, and there's this thin layer of water of משקה טופח mashkeh
tofe'ach
that connects it. If I go into this מקווה, mikvah, I'm not
טהור. tahor. We look at it as two bodies of water, not
as one. If this was טופח על מנת להטפיח, tofe'ach al menat
le'hatpi'ach,
if it was a thicker film of water, we'd look at it
as all one big מקווה mikvah and even if I went here
I'd be טהור. tahor. Okay, so that's what you need it for
חיבור chibur for טומאה tumah and טהרה. taharah. So this says that
these things are not a חיבור chibur for טומאה tumah and טהרה.
taharah. But אשבורן, ashboren, a collected body of water, okay, that sits
between two other bodies, is a חיבור לטומאה ולטהרה. chibur le'tumah u'letaharah.
So that's all very nice for טומאה tumah and טהרה. taharah. We've
seen before that we connect aspects of טומאה tumah and טהרה taharah
to יין נסך, yayin nesech, right? Questions about an עם הארץ, am
ha'aretz, are we concerned about they touched it or not? Certain questions
about what type of a touch of a non-Jew makes it טמא—makes
tamei it יין נסך, yayin nesech, is it like the touch of
a זב? zav? You might remember before there was a question כל...
kol... כל שבזב טמא, kol she'ba'zav tamei, you know, is עושה יין
נסך. oseh yayin nesech. So there are all these connections to do
we do you know so between טומאה לטהרה, tuma letahara, between and
יין נסך. yayin nesech. So what do we say about the cases
of יין נסך? yayin nesech? If you go ahead and this is
going to be this case, right, if the non-Jew touches the wine
at the bottom of this vessel or just we say the wine
at the bottom of the vessel automatically becomes יין נסך yayin nesech
because it's in a non-Jew's vessel or mixed with drops of wine
at the bottom, if ניצוק nitzok is חיבור, chibur, it's like all
of it became יין נסך yayin nesech and that would explain why
the wine left in the funnel is a problem. But if ניצוק
nitzok is not חיבור, chibur, only the stuff at the bottom is
יין נסך yayin nesech and the stuff that remains in the in
the in the funnel is not. So that's exactly our question. So
let's take a look. So אמר רב הונא ניצוק וקטפרס ומשקה טופח
חיבור לעניין יין נסך. amar Rav Huna nitzok ve'kataphres u'mashkeh tofe'ach chibur
le'inyan yayin nesech. It might be that these things are not a
do not are not a unifier for טומאה לטהרה tuma letahara but
they are a unifier and they are considered one unit for יין
נסך. yayin nesech. So אמר ליה רב נחמן לרב הונא מנא לך
הא, amar lei Rav Nachman le'Rav Huna mena lach ha, where do
you get this from? אילימא מדתנן eillima mi'detnan the משנה mishnah says
הניצוק והקטפרס ומשקה טופח אינו חיבור לא לטומאה ולא לטהרה. ha'nitzok ve'ha'kataphres
u'mashkeh tofe'ach eino chibur lo le'tuma ve'lo le'tahara. It says that these
things are not a combiner for טומאה לטהרה tuma letahara and your
דיוק, diyuk, your inference is לטומאה ולטהרה הוא דלא הוי חיבור הא
לעניין יין נסך הוי
חיבור. le'tuma u'letahara hu dela havei chibur ha le'inyan yayin nesech havei
chibur. For טומאה לטהרה tuma letahara they're not a unifier but for
יין נסך yayin nesech they are. Maybe לטומאה ולטהרה le'tuma u'letahara why
did it use those words? To indicate that there's other things for
which the this does create one unit. He says אימא סיפא, eima
seifa, look at the end of that משנה. mishnah. האשבורן, ha'eshboren, collected
water חיבור לטומאה ולטהרה chibur le'tuma u'letahara does is a unifier. So
should we also read that to say only for טומאה לטהרה? tuma
letahara? לטומאה ולטהרה הוא דהוי חיבור הא לעניין יין נסך לא הוי
חיבור. le'tuma u'letahara hu de'havei chibur ha le'inyan yayin nesech lo havei
chibur. So maybe we should read that to say oh but collected
water works for טומאה לטהרה tuma letahara but it doesn't work for
יין נסך? yayin nesech? That would be crazy. You want to say
יין נסך yayin nesech is stricter, right? So you can't read in
the words of טומאה לטהרה tuma letahara in the משנה mishnah to
imply that the opposite is true by יין נסך. yayin nesech. Then
you would come to contradictory conclusions between the beginning of the משנה
mishnah and the end of the משנה. mishnah. אלא מהא ליכא למשמע
מינה. ela me'ha leika le'mishma minah. You can't figure it out from
that משנה. mishnah. I appreciate that might be your position but you
don't have a basis for that in that משנה. mishnah. But your
position is that יין נסך yayin nesech is stricter than טומאה לטהרה
tuma letahara for these הלכות. halachot. Now what we're really going to
try to figure it out in is based on our משנה. mishnah.
Because saying ניצוק nitzok is a חיבור chibur is the most logical
way of explaining our משנה, mishnah, of explaining why the wine in
the funnel is a problem since the wine in the vessel is
a problem and it's all connected through this pouring.
Okay, תנן, tnan, let's look at our משנה. mishnah. נטל את המשפך
ומדד לתוך צלוחיתו של עובד כוכבים וחזר ומדד לתוך צלוחיתו של ישראל.
natal et ha'mashpach u'madad le'toch tzluchito shel oved kochavim ve'chazar u'madad le'toch
tzluchito shel Yisrael.
אם יש בהן עכבת יין אסור. im yesh bahen akavat yayin assur.
If there're still some drops of wine it's forbidden. Okay, so הא
עכבת יין במאי קא מיתסרא? ha akavat yayin be'mai ka mitsra? Those
drops of wine how'd they become forbidden? They never went into his
vessel. So לאו בניצוק? lav be'nitzok? Obviously it's through the fact that
they're connected to the bottom of the vessel through this sense of
being poured. שמע מינה ניצוק חיבור. shma mina nitzok chibur. So you
can infer from this that ניצוק nitzok is a חיבור. chibur. That
seems like a pretty darn good proof. So הגמרא ha'Gemara says no.
תני רבי חייא. tani Rabbi Chiya. רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya teaches in
his ברייתא braita a way of qualifying this case in the משנה.
mishnah. שפכסתות צלוחיתו she'pachastot tzluchito that the that the that the wine
bottle basically slapped in the face the wine in the wine bottle
slapped the face as it were of the of the what do
you call it of the funnel. Meaning that the reason this is
forbidden is because the drops here don't become forbidden right away as
soon as the wine starts getting poured. No, as the wine starts
getting poured the drops here are totally okay. But the wine keeps
on collecting and collecting and collecting and eventually this fills up and
some of this doubles back into the funnel. So it's actually the
only reason the funnel is a problem is because the wine that's
already in the you know the bottle you know doubled backed into
the funnel and that's why it's a problem but not because it's
connected through this pouring. Alright, so that gets us out of proving
from this that ניצוק nitzok is a חיבור. chibur. So הגמרא ha'Gemara
says
אלא לא פכסה צלוחיתו מאי? ela lo pachsa tzluchito mai? Okay, if
that's true, let's infer from this ברייתא braita the opposite conclusion. אבל
לא פכסה צלוחיתו מאי? aval lo pachsa tzluchito mai? So what would
you say if it didn't the wine in the in the bottle
didn't double back into the funnel? So you would say לא? lo?
You'd say the funnel isn't a problem? If that's true, תיפשוט דניצוק
אינו חיבור. tipshot de'nitzok eino chibur. So let's conclude that ניצוק nitzok
is not a חיבור. chibur. So let’s conclude the opposite. The fact
that we have to limit our case to where the wine doubled
back, let’s assume that if the wine didn’t double back, then it’s
all okay, ניצוק nitzok is not a חיבור. chibbur. That seems to
be a reasonable conclusion from that תוספתא. Tosefta. So the גמרא Gemara
says no. Look. פחסת צלוחיתו תפשוט לך דאסור. pachastat tzluchito tifshot lach
d’assur. No, no, no. What Rabbi Chiya was saying is if the
wine doubled back, it’s definitely forbidden. Then you really have the wine
from the bottle back into the funnel. ניצוק, nitzok, if it didn’t
double back, Rabbi Chiya is implicitly saying תיקו, teiku, I don’t know.
So what you can infer from this is not that if the
wine didn’t double back it’s okay. If you didn’t double back, it’s
not clear whether it’s okay or not okay from Rabbi Chiya, since
Rabbi Chiya says the case that it’s definitely a problem is that
the wine doubled back. Okay, so given our משנה Mishnah we would
assume ניצוק nitzok is a חיבור, chibbur, given Rabbi Chiya we would
assume ניצוק nitzok is not a חיבור, chibbur, or at least that
it’s questionable whether ניצוק nitzok is a חיבור chibbur or not. So
we don’t have an answer. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear.
Let’s do the second case in our משנה. Mishnah. המערה מכלי לכלי,
hame’areh mikli l’kli, you’re pouring from one vessel to the other one.
את שמערה ממנו מותר. et she-me’areh mimenu mutar. Okay, so here you
are, you’re in this case and it just says, forget the, you
know, forget the what-do-you-call-it, forget the funnel, okay, you’re just pouring from
one vessel into the other, okay,
and it says what you’re pouring from is okay, the stuff at
the bottom of the vessel is no good. Okay, again, either because
it’s סתם stam in the vessel of a non-Jew, maybe because it
mixed with some drops of wine, okay, but why is what’s in
here okay? Okay, there’s two questions. A, what’s left in here and
B, what’s the story of not what’s in this vessel and this
vessel but the stuff that’s in midair? Is that okay or not
okay? And this is all the ניצוק nitzok question. This is no
good, if ניצוק nitzok is a חיבור, chibbur, all of this should
be no good as well, okay, because it’s all one unit. So
let’s take a look. Okay. תא שמע המערה מכלי לכלי את שמערה
ממנו מותר. Ta shema, hame’areh mikli l’kli, et she-me’areh mimenu mutar.
What you’re pouring from is okay. הא דביני ביני אסור. ha d’beini
beini assur. But what’s in midair is forbidden. שמע מינה ניצוק חיבור.
shema mina nitzok chibbur. So why is this forbidden? It must be
because ניצוק חיבור. nitzok chibbur. And somehow I guess we assume that
the stuff that’s still in the vessel doesn’t count towards the ניצוק,
nitzok, right? It’s still considered in its own separate space, but the
stuff that’s in midair is part of the ניצוק, nitzok, and since
it says what’s in here is okay, the implication should be that
this is a problem and this is only a problem because of
ניצוק, nitzok, it’s all combined. Okay. שמע מינה ניצוק חיבור. shema mina
nitzok chibbur. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אי ניצוק חיבור אפילו
דגבי דמנא נמי ליתסר. ei nitzok chibbur afilu d’gabei d’mana nami litesar.
You can’t get away with that. If ניצוק nitzok is a חיבור,
chibbur, then even what’s in the pouring vessel is all connected, so
it should all be forbidden. So actually, the opposite is true. Since
it says that what’s in this the pouring vessel is okay, it
makes it pretty clear that ניצוק nitzok is not a חיבור, chibbur,
because otherwise it’s all connected. So the גמרא Gemara says no, that
I can get out of. הא לא קשיא דקמקטף קטופי. ha lo
kashya d’kamkatef kitufei. The case I could be talking about where what’s
left in the vessel is okay is if the guy turns it
over. He starts pouring, okay, basically you’d have to be a quick
actor. He started pouring and this is stage one, and it hasn’t
yet gotten into this vessel, okay, and then stage number two is
he rights this thing back up, okay, and the wine here still,
I don’t even know if this is possible, I guess if you
have enough of a distance, is still passing in midair, okay, and
therefore and then so he he turns this back up, that’s מקטף
קטופי, makatef kitufei, he like breaks the stream, and then stage number
three is that it finally here gets into the vessel. So when
it gets into the vessel, okay, the stuff in the original thing
is okay because it’s not connected, it’s not part of a stream
that’s connected to the bottom of the vessel. You got it? He
broke the stream before the the wine hit the bottom of the
vessel. And that’s why what’s in here is okay. But אין הכי
נמי, ein hachi nami, if he was in the middle of pouring
and it was all like this as it was hitting the bottom,
we would say ניצוק nitzok is a חיבור chibbur and it’s a
problem. So we’re arguing since the משנה Mishnah says this implies that
the stuff in the middle is a problem, that proves ניצוק nitzok
is חיבור. chibbur. And based on this, this actually should also be
a problem, but our scenario is he broke the stream in the
middle. Okay.
אי משום הא, ei mishum ha, let’s read that again.
It says אי ניצוק חיבור אפילו דגבי דמנא נמי ליתסר הא לא
קשיא דקמקטף קטופי. ei nitzok chibbur afilu d’gabei d’mana nami litesar, ha
lo kashya d’kamkatef kitufei. Could be a case where he broke the
stream. So the גמרא Gemara says מכל מקום ניצוק חיבור. mikol makom
nitzok chibbur. Okay, I’ve explained the משנה Mishnah that the stuff in
the middle is a problem because it’s combined, the stuff in midair.
So from the way I read the משנה, Mishnah, ניצוק nitzok is
a חיבור. chibbur. So haven’t I proved it? The receiving vessel, the
one in the receiving vessel is forbidden. So that says, so who
דאסור *d'asur*? It’s the stuff that’s in
the receiving vessel's forbidden. הא דביני ביני שרי shari. *ha d'beini beini
sharei*.
Where are we? Did I skip a line? No. אימא סיפא את
שאירו לתוכו הוא דאסור
הא דביני ביני שרי *eima seifa et she-iru le-tocho
hu d'asur ha d'beini beini sharei*. The line starts with the הא
דביני *ha d'beini*. Of course it starts with כוחא *kocha*. אלא מהא
ליכא למשמע מינה *ela me'hala'ka le'mishma minah*. From here you can’t prove
it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, what was your whole proof
that ניצוק nitzok. *nitzok* was חיבור chibur. *chibur*? Your whole proof was
it says this is okay, which implied that the stuff in midair
is a problem. But the end of the משנה *Mishnah* says the
stuff in the receiving vessel is no good, which implies that the
stuff in midair is okay. All right? You got it? So the
משנה *Mishnah* says this is okay, this is no good, and it
doesn't tell us the status of the stuff in the middle. So
don't say to me the implication is the stuff in the middle
is no good and that proves ניצוק nitzok *nitzok* is חיבור chibur,
*chibur*. No,
there's no clear implication about whether the stuff in midair is good
or not good. Okay, so because we don't know the status of
the stuff in midair, you cannot prove from our משנה *Mishnah* whether
ניצוק nitzok *nitzok* is חיבור chibur *chibur* or not חיבור chibur? *chibur*.
So we're still stuck. You still can't prove it from our משנה
*Mishnah*. All right, let's move on. תא שמע *tashma*, come and hear.
We're across from the תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* כוחא *kocha*, two words in.
תא שמע *tashma*, line starts with word מינה *minah*. תא שמע המערה
מחבית לבור קילוח היורד משפת חבית למטה אסור assur *tashma ha'me'areh mi-chavit
le-vor kilu'ach ha-yored mi-sefas chavit le-mata asur*. So this seems to be
very clear. You are going ahead and you are pouring from your
barrel of wine into a vat of a non-Jew that has in
it, you know, also his wine and יין נסך yayin nesech. *yayin
nesech*. So it's gonna all get mixed up and so on and
it's gonna be forbidden. Okay, so the stream that goes from
the barrel into the well is forbidden. So this is very explicit
that even the midair stream is forbidden. Okay, you got this? Right?
You got it? It's just like this case, except here it is
explicit. What you're pouring into is not a factor in my nice
little pig story, my nice example. Anyway, what you're pouring into is
a well, is a big vat. Okay, you're pouring from your barrel
into the non-Jew's vat. At the bottom of his vat, he's got
some of his own wine here. That's forbidden. Okay,
this is pouring in and it says the stream it says is
forbidden. Okay,
so if the stream is forbidden, that's a pretty good proof that
ניצוק nitzok. *nitzok* is חיבור chibur *chibur*, right? Cause this stream isn't
mixed up with this wine, but we're looking at it all as
one big unit. All right. המערה מחבית לבור קילוח היורד משפת חבית
למטה אסור assur *ha'me'areh mi-chavit le-vor kilu'ach ha-yored mi-sefas chavit le-mata asur*.
So, although it does only say from the edge of the barrel,
which still raises the question why is the stuff in the barrel
not forbidden? But we're going to bracket that for a minute. The
fact that the stream is forbidden seems to show that we're talking
about ניצוק חיבור nitzok chibur. *nitzok chibur*. All right. תרגמה רב ששת
בעובד כוכבים המערה *targema
Rav Sheshes be-oved kochavim ha-me'areh*. No, you got it wrong. It's not
the Jew who's pouring, it's the non-Jew who's pouring. So why does
that matter? So then it doesn't even matter that he's pouring into
a well. The fact that he's just pouring, it's like the standard
example of the non-Jew pouring your לא Lo, מבושל *lo mevushal* wine
at your table, having a non-Jewish waiter. Okay, this is very important
everybody. This is the question of whether can I have a non-Jewish
waiter pour my wine? It's kosher wine. Why can't he pour my
wine? He's not touching it. So the answer is דאתי מכוחו *de'asai
mi'kocho*. Since his energy is causing that wine to move out of
the bottle, it's like he moved the wine. Okay, so this guy
is a non-Jew and because he's a non-Jew, actually pouring into the
well is irrelevant. Because he's a non-Jew, he's moving this wine and
since he's moving, it's the non-Jew pouring your לא מבושל *lo mevushal*
wine for you at your table, that's like he touched that wine
and that's what makes that wine forbidden. It has nothing to do
with the fact that it's going into a well that has also
maybe some problematic wine in it and nothing to do with the
idea of ניצוק חיבור nitzok chibur, *nitzok chibur*. It's not because it's
connected, it's because he's moving that wine. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אי עובד כוכבים המערה אפילו גב דחביתא נמי מיתסר *i oved
kochavim ha-me'areh afilu gav de-chavisa nami mitzar*, which by the way you
could have asked with the what do you call it with the
ניצוק חיבור nitzok chibur *nitzok chibur* as well question, but okay, why
is the stuff in the barrel okay? The stuff in the barrel
is also moving due to his energy, right? As you're pouring out
from that bottle of wine, some goes out of the barrel, but
even the stuff in the bottle
is moving from the bottom of the bottle to the lip of
the bottle. So why is that okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says no. כח דעובד כוכבים מדרבנן הוא. Koach
d'oved kochavim mid'rabbanan hu. The idea that we're concerned about his energy
rather than his touching is all rabbinic. I mean the irony is
this whole thing is rabbinic because the whole thing is about סתם
יינם stam yeinam more than it's about יין נסך. Yayin Nesach. But
anyway, okay. That's all rabbinic. It's only his energy, he's not actually
touching it.
Where were we?
מדרבנן הוא דאסור. Mid'rabbanan hu d'assur. It's only a rabbinic problem. הוא
דנפיק לבראי גזרו ביה רבנן, הוא דלגואי לא גזרו ביה רבנן. Hu
d'nafik l'varai gazru bay rabanan, hu d'ligavai lo gazru bay rabanan. So
since they said the stuff that actually moved out of the bottle,
out of the barrel, and maybe that's the stuff in air that's
easier for him to touch anyway, and it's where the movement is
more visible. So if it goes out of the barrel, it's like
he touched it and it's a problem. The stuff that's still in
the barrel is okay. So by the way, just to pause here
for a moment, you realize what this would mean for a non-Jew
who poured your אינו מבושל eino mevushal wine. If he poured your
אינו מבושל eino mevushal wine, the stuff that came out of the
bottle into your cup, that would be into your glass, that would
be a problem, but the remainder of the stuff in the bottle
based on this should be okay. Does everybody get that? It's a
pretty straightforward point. You could even make a stronger argument in the
case of a wine bottle why the stuff inside the bottle is
okay. You know why? Because there's no way you can get your
finger into the neck of a wine bottle and touch it. It's
even a better case than the barrel. So it's even less like
he touched it. Okay. So is that really true, by the way,
that the stuff in the wine bottle is okay? So I have
to tell you two things. First of all, there's even a debate
of the פוסקים poskim whether if a non-Jew pours, I'm not saying
this הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh for all those who are listening online
or whatever, ask your local Orthodox rabbi the following, but I will
tell you in theory there are opinions that because if we say
nowadays our non-Jews are not really עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei avodah zarah,
they don't really do ניסוך nissuch of wine and so on, that
therefore any non-direct touch is really not a problem. So there are
those of the opinion that this issue here of כח koach and
if somebody pours wine for you that the wine that he pours
in your glass is like he touched it wouldn't apply nowadays to
non-Jews because we say our non-Jews are not like as immersed in
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So some actually are lenient about that בדיעבד,
bedieved, בשעת הדחק, b'shaas hadchak, הפסד מרובה, hefsed merubeh, and so on.
That's in terms of the stuff that's already poured, okay, which for
this גמרא Gemara clearly is a problem. But the stuff that remains
in the bottle, that should certainly be okay. However, there is a
way to say that the stuff that remains in the bottle is
a problem. Why? Because here's what happens. This is going to actually
get, I'm not going to tell you the answer yet, but this
is going to get to our question of ניצוק חיבור. nitzok chibur
So as he's pouring it, this stuff is אסור assur because of
כח. koach. Okay. Then he pours it into, yeah let's have him
pouring it into your nice glass of wine. Okay. Here's your nice
little goblet of wine. I don't know if that's a goblet, whatever
it is. That looks weird. Is that how it looks? Anyway, whatever,
it needs a base, not stable. Anyway,
he's pouring it into your little thing of wine, okay. So now
anyway, you got that in it. So that's אסור assur. because of
כח. koach. Now that that's אסור assur and it's collecting here and
it's connected back, maybe what's left back in your original wine bottle
should be forbidden because of ניצוק. nitzok. Okay, you got it? So
the way to make what's left back in your bottle, our גמרא
Gemara is assuming is arguing ניצוק Nitzok is not חיבור. chibur. And
because ניצוק Nitzok is not חיבור, chibur. only the stuff poured is
a problem because he moved it. The stuff left in the vessel
is okay. But if you add on this the idea of ניצוק
חיבור, Nitzok chibur. then you would say this becomes אסור. assur Once
this becomes אסור assur. and it collects here, it goes back and
it makes that אסור because of ניצוק. Nitzok Okay. So let's take
a look. But our גמרא Gemara is assuming you're not saying ניצוק
חיבור Nitzok chibur. and the only thing that is forbidden is actually
the wine that is in that has been poured. That's been moved
by the non-Jew. All right.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. כח דעובד כוכבים מדרבנן הוא
דאסור. Koach d'oved kochavim mid'rabbanan hu d'assur. A fine. הוא דנפיק לבראי.
Hu d'nafik l'varai. Now הוא דנפיק לבראי גזרו ביה רבנן, הוא דלגואי
לא גזרו ביה רבנן. hu d'nafik l'varai gazru bay rabanan, hu d'ligavai
lo gazru bay rabanan. So we still don't have a conclusion. Is
ניצוק חיבור Nitzok chibur or not? We don't know. We know the
stuff poured is a problem because of כח. koach. We don't know
if there's then an additional problem of ניצוק. Nitzok I should say,
let me just say one sentence and then we'll read the תוספות
Tosfos. that להלכה l'halacha there is a major debate as we'll see
in תוספות. Tosfos. Do we generally פסקן pasken ניצוק Nitzok is חיבור
chibur? or not חיבור? chibur Okay? And again though, especially since that's
heavily debated, there's a סתירה stira in שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch if
we פסקן pasken ניצוק Nitzok is חיבור chibur, by יין נסך. Yayin
Nesach, Alright, when it certainly comes to our cases which is not
יין נסך, Yayin Nesach, it's only סתם יינם, Stam Yeinam, and we're
dealing with non-Jews nowadays etc. again there's like a strong strong reason
to think that we don't say ניצוק חיבור. nitzok chibur. So and
especially in this case, here's a למעשה l'maaseh case, again not למעשה
למעשה, l'maaseh l'maiseh, ask your local Rabbi, but here, your non-Jew is
pouring your אינו מבושל eino mevushal wine for you. So we're going
to assume we won't go by the leniency I mentioned before. We're
going to assume don't drink the wine in your glass. That's like
he touched it, okay, even though it was only indirect. But
להלכה, l'halacha, if this ever happens to you, ask a Rabbi because
if your Rabbi knows laws about סתם יינם, Stam Yeinam, like you
can basically, you know, there's good basis to say you can keep
the rest of the wine in the bottle. Because even if we
say this is a כוחו kocho problem, we're not going to go
back and say it's a ניצוק Nitzok problem because there's a serious
debate if we פסקן pasken ניצוק nitzok all together. And certainly in
this case where there were you know all these other points to
be lenient. It's not יין נסך, Yayin Nesach it's סתם יינם, Stam
Yeinam, he didn't really touch the wine, it's non-Jews nowadays etc. So
in that case there's a very good basis to say that the
wine remaining in the bottle is okay, but if this ever happens
to you, ask your local Rabbi. Okay, looks like you want to
say something Gloria, you know about a case like this? Okay, okay
anyway, I know people who've had cases like this and the Rabbi
did not really know the הלכה halacha well enough. Alright, anyway, so
now let's finish up the גמרא Gemara and then I want to
read a תוספות. Tosfos Okay. אמר
להו רב חסדא להנהו סביסא. Amar lehu Rav Chisda la'hanhu savisa. רב
חסדא Rav Chisda said to the wine sellers, כי כייליתו חמרא לעובדי
כוכבים ki chailisu chamra l'ovdei kochavim when you measure out wine for
the non-Jews,
כתפי קטופי, katfey kitufey, make sure to like break the stream when
you're pouring it, okay, because he doesn't, it sounds like he's concerned
because of ניצוק חיבור. nitzok chibur, It'll hit the bottom of the
vessel, it'll become יין נסך yayin nesech. as it hits the vessel
of the non-Jew and then it'll go back and make everything in
the barrel forbidden. But if you break the stream in midair, you
prevent the connection from going back to the barrel, okay. So that
sounds like we said before and it sounds like ניצוק nitzok is
חיבור. chibur, And if you look at this little רש"י, Rashi, I
don't know where to tell you, it's about 10 lines before the
lines get wide in רש"י, Rashi, maybe 15 lines, it says נפצי
נפוצי, nafsi nifutsey, one line over נפצי נפוצי, nafsi nifutsey, רש"י Rashi
says, דאסור להו בניצוק דסבירא ליה ניצוק חיבור וכן הלכה. d'issur lehu
b'nitzok d'savira leh nitzok chibur v'chein halacha. So there רש"י Rashi says
the הלכה halacha is ניצוק nitzok? is חיבור. chibur. We'll get to
תוספות's Tosafot position in a minute. Okay, so he said to them,
break the stream, so it shouldn't be a ניצוק חיבור nitzok chibur,
problem. אינמי נפצי נפוצי, Inami nafsi nifutsey, or throw the wine into
their into their vessel rather than pour it, so you don't have
a ניצוק nitzok problem. I don't know how that you're going to
manage that it doesn't all spill on the floor. אמר להו רבא
להנהו שפוכאי. Amar lehu Rava la'hanhu shofuchai. רבא Rava said to the
people who would pour wine, you know, maybe these were more the
wholesalers, into the wells of the non-Jews or whatever. כי שפכיתו חמרא
Ki shafchisu chamra when you're pouring out the wine, לא לקרב עובד
כוכבים לסייע בהדייכו. lo l'karev oved kochavim l'sayaya b'hadaichu. Here's a different
issue. Don't, going back to our earlier point about כוחו, kocho, don't
let the non-Jew help you pour out the wine.
Why? דילמא משתליתו, dilma mishtalisu, maybe you'll forget, ושדיתו ליה עליה, v'shadisu
leh aleh, and you'll sort of take a break and then he
might end up doing all the pouring,
וקאתי מכוחו, v'kasi m'kocho, and since he's doing all the pouring and
he's not just assisting, then it's his energy that's moving the wine
and then it's like he touched the wine, ואסור, v'assur, and it'll
be forbidden. Okay. So this is if apparently if you're pouring wine
for Jews. Here you are, you're a Jewish storeowner pouring wine for
Jews. So but don't let your non-Jewish owner do the pouring or
even help you with the pouring because it'll come that he'll do
the pouring and then it'll make the wine forbidden. Okay. Where was
I?
ההוא גברא דאסיק חמרא בגישתא ובת גישתא. Hahu gavra d'assik chamra b'gishta
u'vas gishta. Now there was a certain person who was bringing up
wine through a type of a, this is like a straw that
you're using as a, what's it called, not a siphon, a siphon,
yeah, when you create like a little bit of a of a
of a vacuum and you do it as a siphon, okay. So
you basically had,
you basically had, here's the barrel, okay, here's the straw, like apparently
I don't know, the original straw is a גישתא gishta and then
the one that goes into it and comes out down or whatever
it's called a בת גישתא. bas gishta. Anyway and here's the other
one, okay, and you're getting the wine to like flow through the,
רש"י Rashi clearly defines it as a siphon, right, it's a siphon.
Okay. So, okay, אתא עובד כוכבים אנח ידיה אגישתא. ata oved kochavim
anach yadei a'gishta.
So a non-Jew came and he put his hand on to stop
the flow. So here's the question, he's putting his hand here to
stop the flow, he touches the wine at the... very bottom of
this straw. Is it like he's touching all of the wine that's
in the original barrel, which is sort of like a ניצוק nitzok
issue, although it's a little different than ניצוק nitzok because here it's
actually not flowing down, it's a little bit like, you know, this
here, all of this is like in a state of coming down.
Here, this is like stable and it's being pulled through a siphon,
so it's a little different. So let's see what the הלכה halacha
is.
אסרי רבא לכולי חמרא. Asrei Rava l’kulu chamra. רבא Rava forbade it
all.
אמרו ליה רב פפא לרבא, Amru leih Rav Papa l’Rava, ואמרו ליה
רב אדא בר מתנא לרבא, ve-amru leih Rav Adda bar Matna l’Rava,
ואמרו ליה רבינא לרבא. ve-amru leih Ravina l’Rava. במאי? Be-mai? On what
basis did you forbid it? בניצוק? Be-nitzok? Are you forbidding it on
the basis of ניצוק? nitzok? Are you considering this all like ניצוק
nitzok and one unit? שמע מינה ניצוק חיבור? Shema mina nitzok chibur?
Should we assume that you're saying that ניצוק nitzok is a חיבור?
chibur, So from the fact that he was challenged this way, by
the way, it sounds a little not like רש"י, Rashi, that the
הלכה halacha is that ניצוק nitzok. isn't a חיבור chibur, and that's
why he's saying, "What are you talking about? Is that based on
ניצוק?" nitzok So it sounds like according to them at least ניצוק
nitzok is not a חיבור, chibur, against what רש"י Rashi said before.
Anyway, so his answer was no, even though ניצוק nitzok. might not
be a חיבור, chibur, שאני התם דכולי חמרא אגישתא באגישתא גריר. shani
hatam d'kulei chamra agishta b'agishta garir. Here it's being sort of like
pulled this way, so it's more considered connected. I have to tell
you I don't really fully understand it. Here gravity is pulling it
down and if I touch this we don't say it's connected to
what's up. Here, like a vacuum is pulling it up and through
the straw, and somehow we say because it's actively being pulled through
the straw it is more like it's all connected in one unit.
Somehow I don't really understand why this is more considered one unit
than the case of the, of the, what do you call it,
of the ניצוק. nitzok רש"י Rashi says a little bit that like
here, if you're putting your finger here, you're not doing anything up
there, right? It's this stuff coming down on your finger but you're
not actually touching the stuff up there. Whereas here, because the straw
is what's pulling it out, when you touch the bottom of the
straw, somehow it's like you're sticking your finger into the thing because
this straw is actively pulling it out. So by you touching the
straw, it's like you're going back into the thing itself. So I
sort of can hear it, right? In this way it's falling on
your finger and your finger is not touching the stuff above and
here it's pulling the wine out, so by you touching it it's
like you're in that barrel touching the wine. But anyway, the implication
is without that special case, ניצוק nitzok would not be a
חיבור. chibur.
אמר מר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן, Amar Mar Zutra breih de-Rav Nachman,
one last case, כניסכנין kaniskanin שרי. Okay. If you have this כניסכנין,
kaniskanin, which is basically
a, what do you call it, I have to remind myself what
רש"י Rashi says it is. Oh, it's some type of a thing
that multiple people are like, you know, are like drinking from, okay?
So you've got this thing and it's got like all these straws,
okay? And here's a Jew drinking and here's a non-Jew drinking from
it or whatever. So the non-Jew is drinking and the wine is
going into his mouth, but it's not going back into the vessel.
And you're drinking, so even though you and the non-Jew are all
have your straws into this big tub of wine at the same
time, okay, he is not, you know, it's, he is not touching
the wine that you are drinking. Alright, and I guess it's not
a ניצוק nitzok case even though he's touching it up here, it's
not like he's touching it down here. It's like reverse, reverse ניצוק.
nitzok והני מילי דקדים פסק ישראל. Ve-hanei milei d’kadim pasek Yisrael. That's
only if you stop drinking before him. אבל קדים פסק עובד כוכבים,
Aval kadim pasek oved kochavim, if he stopped drinking before you, some
of the wine that was at the tip of his straw, now
that he's stopped drinking, that wine that his lips touched that didn't
go into his mouth is now going to fall back into the
vessel. Okay. לא, that would not be good. רבה בר רב הונא
איקלע לבי ריש גלותא. Rabbah bar Rav Huna ikla l'bei reish galuta.
שרו ליה למשתא בכניסכנין, Shero leih l'mishta b'kaniskanin, they allowed them to
drink this. איכא דאמרי רבה בר רב הונא גופיה אישתי בכניסכנין, Ika
de-amri Rabbah bar Rav Huna gufeih ishti b'kaniskanin, maybe he himself drank
from it. תוספות Tosafot, wants to know why weren't they afraid, how
did they know who was going to stop first, why weren't they
afraid of that? Anyway, what I want to do is I want
you to look at this תוספות, Tosafot we have one minute left,
about this big issue about ניצוק חיבור. nitzok chibur So he has
a whole discussion, רש"י Rashi פוסק posek ניצוק nitzok חיבור, chibur. רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam פוסק posek ניצוק nitzok is not חיבור, chibur. and
that's only when we're talking about יין נסך. yeyn nesech When we're
talking about סתם יינם stam yeinam maybe we could even be even
more lenient. So if you look at the end of this big
תוספות Tosafot, he says the following, he says,
he goes through the following like this, he says, one, two,
three lines down in the wide lines, in the widest lines of
תוספות, Tosafot he says towards the beginning of the line: והשתא, Ve-hashta,
he says, במקום שיש הפסד גדול, be-makom she-yesh hefsed gadol, if there's
a large loss that will come because the non-Jew touched it and
does it go back and make the rest of the wine that's
in the pouring barrel forbidden and so on, יש לסמוך על דברי
רבינו תם, yesh lismokh al divrei Rabbeinu Tam, להתיר מגע עובד כוכבים
על ידי ניצוק. le-hatir maga oved kochavim al yedei nitzok. You could
be lenient like רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. and say that ניצוק nitzok
is not a problem. אבל בהפסד מועט, Aval behefsed mu'at, if it's
just a small loss, יכול להחמיר כדברי רש״י. yachol l'hachmir k'divrei Rashi.
It's better to be strict like רש״י Rashi and think that ניצוק
nitzok is a problem. Okay, so number one major debate, do we
פוסק pasken in the end ניצוק nitzok is a problem. אמנם, Amnam,
אם משך, im mashach, and now it's very interesting, he gives two
scenarios. אם משך יין מן החבית לתוך כלי שיש בו יין נסך
אם יש בחבית שישים מן היין שבכלי שיש בו נסך ודאי מותר
אפילו מאן דאמר ניצוק חיבור. Im mashach yayin min hachavit l'toch kli
sheyeish bo yeyn nesech, im yeish bachavit shishim min hayayin shebakli shebo
nesech, vadai mutar, afilu man d'amar nitzok chibur. So תוספות Tosafot says,
too bad Michael isn't here because Michael always wants to know הלכה,
halachah, that all this הלכה halachah that wine in wine is a
problem במשהו b'mashehu is only a סתם יינם stam yeinam issue. It's
only a יין נסך yeyn nesech issue. By סתם יינם, stam yeinam,
it goes by the normal הלכות halachos of שישים. shishim. Okay, and
therefore תוספות Tosafot says like this: If you're doing something like this,
and the reason this is a problem is because there are some
drops of יין נסך yeyn nesech here, and this wine is getting
mixed up, תוספות Tosafot, says actually even if you were to say
ניצוק nitzok חיבור, if you're talking about סתם יינם, stam yeinam, this
wine is okay because all ניצוק nitzok חיבור means, it means like
okay, it's like these little drops got mixed with everything. Well guess
what? סתם יינם stam yeinam is בטל בשישים. batel b'shishim. In the
גמרא Gemara it's a problem because the גמרא is talking about יין
נסך and it's במשהו. b'mashehu. So if you consider it that these
drops got mixed with all the wine, then all this wine is
אסור. But if it's סתם יינם stam yeinam and it's בשישים, b'shishim,
then this wine is okay. You got it? So if that's true,
when is ניצוק nitzok ever a problem? So let's finish the תוספות,
Tosafot he
says, דלא גרע חיבור דהאי ניצוק מאילו היה כולו מעורב בחבית שאז
היה בטל בשישים כסתם יינם כמו שפירש רבנו תם. d'lo gara chibur
d'hai nitzok me'ilu haya kulo me'urav bachavit she'az haya batel b'shishim k'stam
yeinam, k'mo sheperush Rabbeinu Tam. רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says סתם יינם
stam yeinam is בטל בשישים. batel b'shishim. So in this case even
if ניצוק nitzok is חיבור, okay, it's just a few drops of
wine that gets mixed up and it's בטל בשישים. batel b'shishim. So
which is the ניצוק nitzok? problem? So here's the ניצוק nitzok problem:
וניצוק דמצר, V'nitzok d'mitzar, the ניצוק nitzok that's a problem, is היכי
דמי כגון שהיה יין מקלח מן החבית ובא עובד כוכבים ונגע בקילוח
שהוא הניצוק
כי האי מיצר למאן דאמר ניצוק חיבור. heichi dami k'gon shehaya yayin
mekalach min hachavit uba oveid kochavim v'naga bakiluach shehu hanitzok, ki hai
mitzar l'man d'amar nitzok chibur. Okay, the ניצוק nitzok question is not
this. The ניצוק nitzok question is comes Mr. Non-Jew while you're pouring
your wine and he touches it over here. So in that case,
if ניצוק is חיבור, it's not a question of a תערובת, ta'aroves,
a mixture. If ניצוק is חיבור, the question is what wine did
he touch? Did he touch just this wine or did he touch
all of this wine? Is this all one unit? So when it's
a question of a תערובת, ta'aroves, a mixture, who cares about ניצוק?
It's all בטל בשישים. batel b'shishim. But when it's a question of
touching, okay, then he says it's like he touched all the wine.
And that's where there's a debate of רש״י Rashi and רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam if ניצוק is חיבור. Okay, ומכל מקום היכא שיש הפסד
מרובה סמכינן אפסק רבנו תם. umikol makom heicha sheyeish hefsed merubeh samchinan
ap'sak Rabbeinu Tam. If there's a הפסד מרובה, hefsed merubeh, then we
can rely on רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam and then we can say
that ניצוק is not a חיבור. So major מחלוקת machlokes whether at
the end of the day we פוסק pasken ניצוק is חיבור. One
last thing, the final thing I'll say is the other תוספות Tosafot
which we won't read inside about the גמרא about don't let the
non-Jew pour it and so on, okay, that is a case where
תוספות Tosafot discusses that issue about does it matter who's doing the
majority of the pouring, whether if the stuff is being poured by
a Jew and a non-Jew, he actually has a scenario, I'll just
end with this scenario. Here we have, this is being poured out,
okay, into my thing, and comes the non-Jew and to speed it
up, he tips it a little bit at a higher angle to
help it all pour out faster. Is that a problem of כוחו?
kocho? Because since he tipped it, it's going faster. Or do we
say since it was going to get into my vessel eventually, it's
not a problem of כוחו. kocho. So the next תוספות explores this
question of the pouring of a non-Jew and when is his pouring
significant, when does his added energy a problem, and when is it
considered the Jew was doing it anyway, it would have happened eventually
anyway, and so on. So this גמרא is huge הלכה למעשה halachah
l'ma'aseh issues about the non-Jew pouring wine for you at your table,
about questions about כוחו kocho and about ניצוק and how much do
we apply this to סתם יינם stam yeinam and how much do
we apply this to the non-Jews we sort of are dealing with
nowadays. Okay, we'll end with this. Yeah, what about beer?